<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<teiHeader xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Kādambarī</title>
            <title type="sub">A HANSEL edition</title>
            <author>Bāṇa Bhaṭṭa</author>
            <author>Bhūṣaṇa Bhaṭṭa</author>
            <respStmt>
                <persName>Andrew Ollett</persName>
                <resp>Creation of machine-readable version for SARIT.</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
                <persName>Tyler Neill</persName>
                <resp>Creation/Synthesis of new machine-readable version for HANSEL.</resp>
            </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>

        <publicationStmt>
            <authority>HANSEL: Human-Accessible NLP-ready Sanskrit E-text Library</authority>
            <availability status="restricted">
                <p>Copyright 2025 Tyler Neill.</p>
                <p>
                    <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/" type="licence">Distributed by <ref target="https://hansel-library.info" type="url">HANSEL</ref> under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</ref>
                </p>
                <p>Under this licence, you are free <list>
                        <item>to Share — to copy and redistribute the material in any medium or format</item>
                        <item>to Adapt — remix, transform, and build upon the material</item>
                    </list></p>
                <p>Under the following terms:</p>
                <p>
                    <list>
                        <item>Attribution — You must give appropriate credit , provide a link to the license, and indicate if changes were made . You may do so in any reasonable manner, but not in any way that suggests the licensor endorses you or your use.</item>
                        <item>NonCommercial — You may not use the material for commercial purposes .</item>
                        <item>ShareAlike — If you remix, transform, or build upon the material, you must distribute your contributions under the same license as the original.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>More information and fuller details of this license are given on the Creative
                    Commons website.</p>
                <p>HANSEL assumes no responsibility for unauthorised use that infringes the
                    rights of any copyright owners, known or unknown.</p>
            </availability>
            <date when="2025-10-15">October 15, 2025</date>
        </publicationStmt>

        <notesStmt>
            <note>This famous literary work was begun by Bāṇa Bhaṭṭa (so-called Pūrvabhāga, Peterson ed. pp. 1–237) and finished posthumously by his son Bhūṣaṇa Bhaṭṭa (Uttarabhāga, pp. 239–369). The complete work is extant. Peterson's edition, on which this e-text is based, added paragraph breaks as further structure. Later editions also added headers to indicate beginnings of significant portions of the story, but these are not used here. The overall story is that of a romance between the two characters Candrāpīḍa and Kādambarī, but the book also contains innumerable side stories.</note>
        </notesStmt>

        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
                <title>Kâdambarî</title>
                <editor>Peterson, Peter</editor>
                <imprint>
                    <publisher>Government Central Book Depôt</publisher>
                    <pubPlace>Bombay</pubPlace>
                    <date>1885</date>
                </imprint>
            </bibl>
            <series>
                <title level="s">Bombay Sanskrit Series</title>
                <biblScope>No. XXIV</biblScope>
                <note>No. XXIV was printed in three distinct forms:
                    <ul>
                        <li>1883 (first edition, included Introduction)</li>
                        <li>1885 (revised edition, text only)</li>
                        <li>1889 (simple reset of 1885)</li>
                    </ul>
                </note>
            </series>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>

    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
          <p id="file-creation-method">
              I (Tyler Neill) produced this HANSEL edition by first running a PDF of the 1885 edition through both Google Cloud Vision OCR (via Skrutable) and Gemini 2.5 Flash (via Dharmamitra). These two OCR outputs were then automatically harmonized using Gemini 2.5 Pro (via direct API) and a custom prompt. Finally, the harmonized OCR output was contrasted against the previous version by Andrew Ollett (which was in fact based on 1885/1889 as well) using Meld, and differences were reconciled individually with reference to the PDF.
          </p>
          <p id="transliteration">
              The published edition from which this e-text was transcribed is printed in the Devanāgarī script. The electronic text below is in a lossless transliteration using the Latin alphabet. The transliteration scheme used is the IAST (<ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_Alphabet_of_Sanskrit_Transliteration">The International Alphabet of Sanskrit Transliteration</ref>). IAST differs in small ways from ISO 15919, but is preferred by most working Sanskrit scholars. Conversion of this file to ISO 15919 can be achieved by performing the following replacements throughout the file:
               <ul>
                   <li><code>ṛ -> r̥</code></li>
                   <li><code>ḷ -> l̥</code></li>
                   <li><code>ṃ -> ṁ </code></li>
                   <li><code>e -> ē</code></li>
                   <li><code>o -> ō</code></li>
               </ul>
          </p>
          <p id="word-division">
              Text division is as Devanāgarī ("ityevam" not "ity evam".)
          </p>
          <p id="error-markup">
              Errors discovered in the source edition and fixed in this electronic version are marked with the following:
              <ul>
                  <li>
                      For replacements:
                      <choice>
                          <sic>before</sic>
                          <corr>after</corr>
                      </choice>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                      For mere deletions: <del/>
                  </li>
                  <li>
                      For mere additions: <supplied/>.
                  </li>
              </ul>
              Unclear or suspect material is marked with <unclear/>.
          </p>
          <p id="intermediate-textual-units">
              <p>
                  Prose paragraphs are enclosed in the normal <tag>p</tag> tags. Verse passages are grouped enclosed in line-group tag <tag>lg</tag>, with one parent <tag>lg</tag> for groups of verses, and verse halves are individually tagged with <tag>l</tag>. <tag>p</tag> and parent <tag>lg</tag> have location markers.
              </p>
            </p>
        </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>

    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2022-02-01" who="Andrew Ollett">Initial OCR (1885/9 edition used, not 1883 as noted), some proofreading, XML markup for SARIT, uploaded to GitHub.</change>
        <change when="2024–2025" who="Tyler Neill">Second OCR (1885 edition, 2 models, merged with AI), manual reconciliation of differences relative to previous version, some more proofreading, markup for HANSEL.</change>
    </revisionDesc>

</teiHeader>
